Can we, as adults, grow new nerve cells?
هل بإمكاننا، نحن البالغين، إنتاج خلايا عصبية جديدة؟
There's still some confusion about that question,
ما زال هناك بعض الاضطراب بخصوص هذا السؤال،
as this is a fairly new field of research.
بما أنه مجال جديد نسبيا في البحث.
For example, I was talking to one of my colleagues, Robert,
مثلا، كنت أتحدث مع أحد زملائي و هو روبرت،
who is an oncologist,
و يعمل طبيب أورام،
and he was telling me,
وقال لي،
"Sandrine, this is puzzling.
"ساندرين، هذا أمر محيّر.
Some of my patients that have been told they are cured of their cancer
بعض مرضاي الذين تمّ إخبارهم بأنهم شفوا من مرض السرطان
still develop symptoms of depression."
ما يزالون يشكون من أعراض الاكتئاب."
And I responded to him,
وأجبته،
"Well, from my point of view that makes sense.
"حسنا، من وجهة نظري يبدو هذا معقولا.
The drug you give to your patients that stops the cancer cells multiplying
الدواء الذي تعطيه لمرضاك والذي يحدّ من تكاثر الخلايا السرطانية
also stops the newborn neurons being generated in their brain."
يوقف أيضا الخلايا العصبيّة حديثة الولادة التي يتم إنشاؤها في الدماغ."
And then Robert looked at me like I was crazy and said,
نظر إلي روبرت كما لو أنني كنت مجنونة وقال لي،
"But Sandrine, these are adult patients --
"ولكن ساندرين، هؤلاء مرضى بالغون --
adults do not grow new nerve cells."
و البالغون لا ينتجون خلايا عصبية جديدة."
And much to his surprise, I said, "Well actually, we do."
وعلى قدر مفاجئته، قلت له، "في الحقيقة، نحن نقوم بذلك".
And this is a phenomenon that we call neurogenesis.
وهذه ظاهرة نسمّيها تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
[Neurogenesis]
[تكوّن الخلايا العصبية]
Now Robert is not a neuroscientist,
حاليا روبرت ليس عالم أعصاب،
and when he went to medical school he was not taught what we know now --
وعندما التحق بكلية الطب لم يتعلم ما نعرفه الآن --
that the adult brain can generate new nerve cells.
بأن البالغين يمكنهم إنتاج خلايا عصبية جديدة.
So Robert, you know, being the good doctor that he is,
و لأن روبرت طبيب جيد،
wanted to come to my lab
فقد أراد أن يأتي إلى مختبري
to understand the topic a little bit better.
ليفهم الموضوع أكثر.
And I took him for a tour
وقد أخذته في جولة
of one of the most exciting parts of the brain
في الجزء الأكثر إثارة من الدماغ
when it comes to neurogenesis --
عندما يتعلق الأمر بتكوين الخلايا العصبية --
and this is the hippocampus.
وهو "الحُصين".
So this is this gray structure in the center of the brain.
إذن هذا هيكل رمادي في وسط الدماغ.
And what we've known already for very long,
وما نعرفه منذ مدة طويلة.
is that this is important for learning, memory, mood and emotion.
هو أن هذا الجزء مهم للتعلّم والذاكرة والمزاج والأحاسيس.
However, what we have learned more recently
ومع ذلك، ما تعلمناه مُؤخّرا
is that this is one of the unique structures of the adult brain
أن هذا هو الجزء الوحيد من الدماغ
where new neurons can be generated.
حيث يمكن تكوين الخلايا العصبية الجديدة.
And if we slice through the hippocampus
وإذا قطعنا "الحُصين"
and zoom in,
ونظرنا داخله،
what you actually see here in blue
فما يُمكن أن تراه هنا باللون الأزرق
is a newborn neuron in an adult mouse brain.
هو خلية عصبية جديدة بدماغ فأر بالغ.
So when it comes to the human brain --
حين يتعلق الأمر بدماغ الإنسان --
my colleague Jonas Frisén from the Karolinska Institutet,
زميلي جوناس فريزان من معهد كارولينسكا،
has estimated that we produce 700 new neurons per day
قدّر إنتاج الخلايا العصبية الجديدة ب700 خلية في اليوم
in the hippocampus.
في "الحُصين".
You might think this is not much,
ربما ستُخمّن بأن هذا ليس كثيرا،
compared to the billions of neurons we have.
مقارنة بمليارات الخلايا العصبية التي لدينا.
But by the time we turn 50,
ولكن مع مرور الوقت وبلوغنا 50،
we will have all exchanged the neurons we were born with in that structure
نكون قد استبدلنا كل الخلايا العصبية التي وُلدنا بها في ذلك الجزء
with adult-born neurons.
بخلايا عصبية بالغة.
So why are these new neurons important and what are their functions?
لم تُعتبر هذه الخلايا العصبية الجديدة مهمة وما مهامها؟
First, we know that they're important for learning and memory.
أولا، نعرف بأنها مهمة للتعلّم والذاكرة.
And in the lab we have shown
وفي المختبر بيّنا
that if we block the ability of the adult brain
أنه عندما نوقف قدرة الدماغ لإنسان بالغ
to produce new neurons in the hippocampus,
على إنتاج خلايا عصبية جديدة "بالحُصين".
then we block certain memory abilities.
فإننا بالتالي نوقف قدرات معينة للذاكرة.
And this is especially new and true for spatial recognition --
وهذا جديد وحقيقي بالنسبة لتمييز المكان --
so like, how you navigate your way in the city.
اذن مثل التنقل بالمدينة.
We are still learning a lot,
نحن مازلنا نتعلم الكثير،
and neurons are not only important for memory capacity,
والخلايا العصبية ليست مهمة فقط لقدرات الذاكرة،
but also for the quality of the memory.
ولكن لجودة الذاكرة أيضا.
And they will have been helpful to add time to our memory
وستساعد هذه الخلايا على إضافة مزيد من الوقت لذاكرتنا
and they will help differentiate very similar memories, like:
كما ستساعد على التفرقة بين ذكريات مشابهة، مثل:
how do you find your bike
كيف تجد دراجتك التي
that you park at the station every day in the same area,
تضعها في المحطة كل يوم في نفس المكان،
but in a slightly different position?
ولكن في وضعية مختلفة قليلا؟
And more interesting to my colleague Robert
والمثير للاهتمام بالنسبة لزميلي روبرت
is the research we have been doing on neurogenesis and depression.
هو البحث الذي نقوم به في ما يتعلق بتكوين الخلايا العصبية والاكتئاب.
So in an animal model of depression,
و في نموذج حيواني للاكتئاب،
we have seen that we have a lower level of neurogenesis.
لاحظنا وجود انخفاض في مستوى تكوين الخلايا العصبية.
And if we give antidepressants,
وعند إعطائه مضادات للاكتئاب،
then we increase the production of these newborn neurons,
يرتفع إنتاج الخلايا العصبية الجديدة،
and we decrease the symptoms of depression,
وتنخفض أعراض الاكتئاب،
establishing a clear link between neurogenesis and depression.
وبالتالي إنشاء علاقة واضحة بين تكوين الخلايا العصبية والاكتئاب.
But moreover, if you just block neurogenesis,
وأيضا، إذا منعت تكوين الخلايا العصبية،
then you block the efficacy of the antidepressant.
فقد منعت تأثير مضادات الاكتئاب.
So by then, Robert had understood
لذلك فهم روبرت
that very likely his patients were suffering from depression
أنه من المرجح جدا أن يكون مرضاه يُعانون من الاكتئاب
even after being cured of their cancer,
حتى بعد شفائهم من مرض السرطان،
because the cancer drug had stopped newborn neurons from being generated.
لأن الدواء المضاد للسرطان قد منع الخلايا العصبية الجديدة من التكوّن.
And it will take time to generate new neurons
وتكوّن خلايا عصبية جديدة فعّالة
that reach normal functions.
يستغرق وقتا.
So, collectively, now we think we have enough evidence
الآن نعتقد بالإجماع بأننا نملك الدليل الكافي
to say that neurogenesis is a target of choice
لنقول بأن تكوين الخلايا العصبية هو هدف مختار
if we want to improve memory formation or mood,
إذا أردنا تحسين تشكيل الذاكرة والمزاج،
or even prevent the decline associated with aging,
أو حتى الوقاية من انخفاضهما نتيجة الشيخوخة،
or associated with stress.
أوالاكتئاب.
So the next question is:
إذن السؤال التالي هو:
can we control neurogenesis?
هل يمكننا التحكم بتكوين الخلايا العصبية؟
The answer is yes.
الجواب هو نعم.
And we are now going to do a little quiz.
والآن سنقوم باختبار صغير.
I'm going to give you a set of behaviors and activities,
سوف أعطيكم مجموعة من السلوكيات والأنشطة،
and you tell me if you think they will increase neurogenesis
وسوف تخبرونني ما إذا كانت تساهم في تعزيز تكوّن الخلايا العصبية
or if they will decrease neurogenesis.
أو انخفاض تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
Are we ready?
هل نحن مستعدون؟
OK, let's go.
حسنا، فلنبدأ.
So what about learning?
ماذا عن التعلّم؟
Increasing?
هل يزيدها؟
Yes.
نعم.
Learning will increase the production of these new neurons.
سيساهم التعلم في تعزيز تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
How about stress?
ماذا عن التوتر؟
Yes, stress will decrease the production of new neurons in the hippocampus.
نعم سيتسبب التوتر في انخفاض تكوّن الخلايا العصبية بالحُصين.
How about sleep deprivation?
ماذا عن الحرمان من النوم؟
Indeed, it will decrease neurogenesis.
في الواقع، سيزيد من انخفاض تكوين الخلايا العصبية.
How about sex?
ماذا عن ممارسة الجنس؟
Oh, wow!
أو، واو!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Yes, you are right, it will increase the production of new neurons.
نعم، أنتم على حق، سيرتفع تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
However, it's all about balance here.
ومع ذلك، كل شيء يتعلق بالتوازن هنا.
We don't want to fall in a situation --
لا نريد أن نكون في حالة --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
about too much sex leading to sleep deprivation.
ممارسة الكثير من الجنس مما يؤدي إلى حرمانكم من النوم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
How about getting older?
ماذا عن التقدم في السن؟
So the neurogenesis rate will decrease as we get older,
مع تقدمنا في السن سوف ينخفض تكوين الخلايا العصبية،
but it is still occurring.
ولكن ما تزال الخلايا تتكون.
And then finally, how about running?
وأخيرا، ماذا عن الركض؟
I will let you judge that one by yourself.
سوف أترككم تحكمون على ذلك بأنفسكم.
So this is one of the first studies
إذن هذه دراسة من أول الدراسات
that was carried out by one of my mentors, Rusty Gage from the Salk Institute,
التي قام بها أحد المدربين وهو روستي غايج من معهد سالك،
showing that the environment can have an impact
و تدلّ على أن للبيئة تأثير
on the production of new neurons.
على إنتاج الخلايا العصبية الجديدة.
And here you see a section of the hippocampus of a mouse
وهنا ترون مقطعا لحصين فأر
that had no running wheel in its cage.
لا يملك عجلة دوارة بقفصه.
And the little black dots you see are actually newborn neurons-to-be.
وتلك النقاط المسودة قليلا التي ترونها هي في الحقيقة خلايا عصبية جديدة ستتكون.
And now, you see a section of the hippocampus of a mouse
والآن ترون مقطعا لحصين فأر
that had a running wheel in its cage.
يملك عجلة دوارة بقفصه.
So you see the massive increase
و تلاحظون الارتفاع الهائل
of the black dots representing the new neurons-to-be.
للنقاط السوداء التي تمثل الخلايا العصبية الجديدة التي ستتكون
So activity impacts neurogenesis, but that's not all.
إذن يتأثر تكوين الخلايا العصبية بالأنشطة. ولكن ليس هذا فقط.
What you eat will have an effect
ما ستأكله سيكون له تأثير
on the production of new neurons in the hippocampus.
على إنتاج الخلايا العصبية الجديدة بالحُصين.
So here we have a sample of diet --
وهنا لدينا مثال لنظام غذائي --
of nutrients that have been shown to have efficacy.
لمغذيات ثبت تأثيرها.
And I'm just going to point a few out to you:
وسأذكر بعضا منها:
Calorie restriction of 20 to 30 percent will increase neurogenesis.
حد السعرات الحرارية ب20 إلى 30% سيساهم في ارتفاع تكوين الخلايا العصبية.
Intermittent fasting -- spacing the time between your meals --
الصوم المتقطع -- تخصيص فترات استراحة بين وجبات الطعام --
will increase neurogenesis.
سيساهم في ارتفاع تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
Intake of flavonoids,
تناول الفلافنويد،
which are contained in dark chocolate or blueberries,
الموجود بالشوكلاتة السوداء أو التوت الأزرق،
will increase neurogenesis.
سيساهم في ارتفاع تكوّن الخلايا العصبية
Omega-3 fatty acids,
الأحماض الدهنية أوميغا 3،
present in fatty fish, like salmon,
الموجودة بالاسماك الدهنية، مثل السلمون،
will increase the production of these new neurons.
سيساهم في ارتفاع تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
Conversely, a diet rich in high saturated fat
على عكس ذلك، نظام غذائي غني بالدهون المشبعة
will have a negative impact on neurogenesis.
سيكون له تأثير سلبي على تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
Ethanol -- intake of alcohol -- will decrease neurogenesis.
إيثانول --و تناول الكحول -- سيساهمان في انخفاض تكوّن الخلايا العصبية.
However, not everything is lost;
ولكن رغم ذلك، لا يتم فقدان كل شيء:
resveratrol, which is contained in red wine,
لقد تبين بأن ريزفيراترول الموجود بالنبيذ الأحمر،
has been shown to promote the survival of these new neurons.
يُعزّز بقاء هاته الخلايا العصبية على قيد الحياة.
So next time you are at a dinner party,
في المرة القادمة و في حفلة عشاء،
you might want to reach for this possibly "neurogenesis-neutral" drink.
ربما قد ترغب في الحصول على هذا الشراب "المكون للخلايا العصبية"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then finally, let me point out the last one --
وأخيرا، دعوني أذكر شيئا أخيرا --
a quirky one.
شيئا غريبا.
So Japanese groups are fascinated with food textures,
اليابانيون مفتونون بتركيبة الغذاء،
and they have shown that actually soft diet impairs neurogenesis,
ولقد بينوا بأن النظام الغذائي اللين يُتلف تكوين الخلايا العصبية،
as opposed to food that requires mastication -- chewing -- or crunchy food.
مُقابل الغذاء الذي يتطلب المضغ أو الطعام المقرمش.
So all of this data,
كل هذه البيانات،
where we need to look at the cellular level,
حيث يتعين علينا أن ننظر على المستوى الخلوي،
has been generated using animal models.
قد تم جمعها من خلال استعمال النماذج الحيوانية.
But this diet has also been given to human participants,
ولكن تم اتباع هذا النظام الغذائي من قبل مشاركين من البشر،
and what we could see is that the diet modulates memory and mood
وما يمكن أن نراه هنا هو أن النظام الغذائي ينظم الذاكرة والمزاج
in the same direction as it modulates neurogenesis,
في نفس الاتجاه كما ينظم تكوين الخلايا العصبية،
such as: calorie restriction will improve memory capacity,
مثل: الحد من السعرات الحرارية سيُعزّز قدرة الذاكرة،
whereas a high-fat diet will exacerbate symptoms of depression --
بينما نظام غذائي غني بالدهنيات المشبعة سيُؤدي إلى تفاقم أعراض الاكتئاب --
as opposed to omega-3 fatty acids, which increase neurogenesis,
وهو معاكس للأحماض الدهنية أوميغا3 تزيد من تكوّن الخلايا العصبية،
and also help to decrease the symptoms of depression.
كما تساعد على انخفاض أعراض الاكتئاب.
So we think that the effect of diet
لذلك نظن أن تأثير النظام الغذائي
on mental health, on memory and mood,
على الصحة العقلية والذاكرة والمزاج،
is actually mediated by the production of the new neurons in the hippocampus.
في الحقيقة يتمثل في تكوّن الخلايا العصبية الجديدة في الحصين.
And it's not only what you eat,
وهو ليس فقط ما تأكله،
but it's also the texture of the food, when you eat it
ولكن أيضا تركيبة الغذاء عندما تأكله
and how much of it you eat.
والكمية التي تأكلها.
On our side -- neuroscientists interested in neurogenesis --
من جهتنا -- نحن أخصائيو الجهاز العصبي المهتمون بتكوّن الخلايا العصبية --
we need to understand better the function of these new neurons,
نحن بحاجة إلى فهم أفضل لكيفية عمل هذه الخلايا العصبية،
and how we can control their survival and their production.
وكيفية التحكم في بقائها على قيد الحياة وإنتاجها.
We also need to find a way to protect the neurogenesis of Robert's patients.
و بحاجة أيضا إلى إيجاد وسيلة لحماية تكوّن الخلايا العصبية لمرضى روبرت.
And on your side --
ومن جهتكم --
I leave you in charge of your neurogenesis.
أترك لكم المسؤولية تكوّن خلاياكم العصبية
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Margaret Heffernan: Fantastic research, Sandrine.
مارغريت هيفمان: بحث رائع، ساندرين.
Now, I told you you changed my life --
والآن، لقد أخبرتك أنك غيّرت حياتي --
I now eat a lot of blueberries.
حاليا آكل الكثير من العنب البري.
Sandrine Thuret: Very good.
ساندرين ثورات: جيد جدا.
MH: I'm really interested in the running thing.
مارغريت هيفمان: أنا مهتمة بالركض.
Do I have to run?
هل علي أن أركض؟
Or is it really just about aerobic exercise,
أو هل يخص هذا التمارين الرياضية،
getting oxygen to the brain?
فقط لوصول الأكسجين إلى الدماغ؟
Could it be any kind of vigorous exercise?
هل من الممكن أن يكون أيا من التمارين القوية؟
ST: So for the moment,
ساندرين ثورات: حاليا،
we can't really say if it's just the running itself,
لا يمكن أن نجزم إن كان الركض نفسه،
but we think that anything that indeed will increase the production --
ولكن نعتقد أن في الواقع أي شيء سيُساهم في ارتفاع الإنتاج --
or moving the blood flow to the brain,
أو سيُوجّه تدفق الدم إلى الدماغ،
should be beneficial.
سيكون مفيدا.
MH: So I don't have to get a running wheel in my office?
مارغريت : إذن لا يجب أن أملك جهاز سير في مكتبي؟
ST: No, you don't!
ساندرين : لا ينبغي عليك.
MH: Oh, what a relief! That's wonderful.
مارغريت : آه، كم هذا مريح، هذا رائع.
Sandrine Thuret, thank you so much.
ساندرين ثورات، شكرا لك جزيلا.
ST: Thank you, Margaret.
ساندرين : شكرا مارغرين.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)